Guide to the Paper Tiger Television Archive, ca. 1981-2014 MSS.276
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series VII: Video recordings
  - Subseries A: PTTV - Broadcast Videotapes
    - Shelia Row Botham Reads The Star - Edit Master, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0130)
      Sheila Rowboatham peeks into the royal families closet in her analysis of British news tabloid, "The Star." With "Homicide" star, Melissa Leo playing a secretary.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #130
    - Herb Schiller On Wall Street: Schiller Smashes The Crash, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0131)
      Herb Schiller Smashes the Crash
      Herb Schiller talks about the boons of 1980's America in which he identifies Reganomics and high technology as the primary contributors to the Stock Market crash of 1987.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #134
    - Modern Bride - Edit Master, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0132)
      Darryl Leo Reads "Modern Bride": Get Me to the Bank on Time
      Darryl Leo gives a critical reading of "Modern Bride" magazine.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #135
    - Oliver's Army: What Wasn't heard In The Hearings with Eric Mendelsohn - Master, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0133)
      Oliver's Army With Eric Mendelson: What Wasn't in the Hearings
      Eric Mendelson uncovers what wasn't in the Iran-Contra hearings.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #136
    - Anilmals in Mass Media: Images of A Schizophrenic Society - Master, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0134)
      Animals in Mass Media: Images of a Schizophrenic Society
      John Sanbonmatsu forges the link between the stereotyping of animals in the mass media and the commodification, exploitation, categorization, and regulation of animals by powerful interests in today's society. Says Sanbonmatsu: "Animals are a diorama we construct for ourselves."
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #137
    - P.W.A.C. Talks Back! - New Edited Master, 1987 (Box 61, Media ID: 276.0135)
      PWAC Talks Back
      Max Navarre talks about the People With AIDS Coalition's publications.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #138
    - William Kunstler Reads The Constitution - Master, 1988; cuid39072 (Box 62, U-matic ID: 276.0136)
      William Kunstler Reads The U.S. Constitution
      William Kunstler looks at the people who signed the Constitution and asks who was left out: Blacks, Indians, Women and Poor people. He also looks at the erosion of the principles stated in the Bill of Rights, such as freedom of press, of due process of law, and right to legal counsel. The show closes with a performance of legendary New York punk band A.P.P.L.E. based on Kunstler's sonnets about the erosion of rights and liberties.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #140
    - Vinnie Mosco Goes Home Shopping - Master, December 1987 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0137)
      Vinnie Mosco Goes Home Shopping
      Vinnie Mosco takes on the Home Shopping Network. In recreating the products and sales techniques of the Home Shopping Channel, Mosco shows how this absurd cultural phenomenon is rapidly becoming a way of life for millions of Americans; however, the cheap merchandise and comfortable experience that home shopping provides is leading to the reduction and marginalization of the American work force. Mosco finally reveals the impending danger behind America's obsession with HSN to be nothing less than the onset of corporate slavery in which corporations are selling people to people.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #141
    - Vinnie Mosco Goes Home Shopping - Master 2, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0138)
    - Fashions Of The Times - Lorenn Glenn Davitian - Master, 1987 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0139)
      Fashions of The "Times": A Critical Review With Lauren-Glenn Davitian
      Lauren Glenn-Davitian examines the photographs of New York Times Fashion supplement, asking "Who is this magazine for?" On every page of the magazine, Glenn-Davitian discovers representations of submissive and isolated women. The show ends with a critique of the mini-series "I'll Take Manhattan."
      1987 TRT: 31 minutes #142
    - Fighting Brothers: Black/White Unity In Popular American Culture with Jim Kavanagh - Edit Master, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0140)
      Jim Kavanagh discusses Fighting Brothers: Black/White Unity in Popular American Culture
      Kavanagh discusses race as it relates to popular culture.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #143
    - The Pedogogy Of Telecommunications or Teaching TV - Master (unedited), 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0141)
      The Pedagogy of Telecommunications: Teaching TV with Media Professors from around The Nation
      Inspired by and produced during a conference hosted by the Center for Twentieth Century Studies at University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, this collaboration between Paper Tiger and MATA (Milwaukee Access Television Association) includes presentations by numerous scholars including John Caughie, Hillary Radner, Annie Goldson and Dee Dee Haleck. Drawing on theory from such fields as literary studies, film studies, and political science this small group of media studies academics give short presentations on various aspects of this (then) new way of analyzing television, ranging from exploring the pleasure one draws from TV what it is to teach television studies, from the value of public access to the geographical "front of pedagogy" in television studies. The programs construction features experimental editing, several original songs about television, and excerpts from industry made instructional videos which documents the shift that was taking place (and which has continued to this day) from practice-based media studies to theory-based media studies. Produced at a workshop at the Center for Twentieth Century Studies at the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee and MATA (Milwaukee Access Television Association).
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #144
    - Michael Harrington Looks At Democracy - Master, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0142)
      Michael Harrington Looks at Democracy: The Two Party System and the Future of the Democrats
      Michael Harrington looks at the two-party system and the future of democracy.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #145
    - Militarism In America After Platoon, Produced by Jang Cottis, Margaret Difani, Bob Kinney, John Walden - Audio: mono 2 channels, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0143)
      Militarism in America After "Platoon"
      Professor Rick Berg and San Diego activist Carol Jahnkow identify the unnoticed presence of militarism in American society. Berg examines the way in which the film Platoon (and others like it) have become the most widely accepted historical realities of the Vietnam War, so much so that they have almost completely displaced the actual event. Carol Jahnkow describes the massive military build up that has been taking place in the San Diego Harbor. This video provides a varied look at the way in which military culture and the production of war have become seemingly innocuous part of our daily lives.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #146
    - Militarism In America After Platoon - Edit Master, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0144)
    - The Campaign Miniseries 1988 with Daniel Marcus - Edit Master (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0145)
      Daniel Marcus Watches the Campaign Miniseries '88
      Daniel Marcus draws parallels between how TV producers and Presidential campaign advisors use the same motifs and tactics to create a popular show. He argues that through the image-based TV medium that does not appeal to the rational mind, a campaign can create a presidential image by touting abstract qualities; but by using the techniques from the entertainment industry it is possible for producers to create presidential characters to which the audience can relate in a more direct way just as they do with sitcom and TV drama characters every night though the set in their living room. Marcus identifies the same plot and character qualities on the "Ronald Reagan Show", running for eight years at the time and quite popular, to the those already familiar to US audience of a sitcom dad with a little John Wayne thrown in for foreign policy. Often time the president is defined by his supporting cast- ie his cabinet, just as the Mary Tyler Moore character is defined in relation to others on the show. When critical issues such as the economy come into play, a president will be more successful if he can be equated with a traditional authority character who inspires confidence just as characters in a familiar TV drama.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #148
    - Robbie Conal Plasters Manhattan - Edit Master, 1987 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0146)
      Robbie Conal Plasters Manhattan: Street Art Attacks Soho
      Street Art cuts loose in the streets of New York City.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #149
    - Neil Lazarus, Catherine Saalfield, Kelly Anderson Read The Weekly Mail - Edit Master, 1987 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0147)
      Kelly Anderson, Neil Lazarus and Catherine Saalfield Read "The Weekly Mail"
      Analysis of an anti-apartheid South African newspaper with anti-censorship strategies and a non-racial social democratic vision.
      1987 TRT: 28 minutes #150
    - Born To Be Sold: Martha Rosler Reads The Strange Case of Baby S/M - Original Edit Master, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0148)
      Born To Be Sold: Martha Rosler Reads the Strange Case of Baby S/M
      Martha Rosler tackles the case of a surrogate mother, Mary Beth Whitehead, as represented by the main-stream media. This tape uncovers the class and gender bias of the media coverage and the courts. Extra inventive graphics and kooky dress-up illustrates Rosler's analysis of the court battle, waged within the tricky issue of contemporary reproductive control in America.
      1988 TRT: 35 minutes #151
    - Born To Be Sold: Martha Rosler Reads The Strange Case of Baby S/M - Public Access Master, 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0149)
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #151
    - Simon Watney Speaks About Clause 29 & Homophobia In The U.K., 1988 (Box 62, Media ID: 276.0150)
      Simon Watney Says No to Section 28
      Simon Watney takes on the Iron Lady and The UK Press on homophobia and the AIDS pandemic.
      1988 TRT: 28 minutes #153
    - The Bicentennial Will Not Be Televised! - Master, 1988 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0151)
      The Bicentennial Will Not Be Televised
      This video serves as a critique of Australia's 200th year celebration, one that completely overlooked the history of imperialism and colonization of its native peoples. In 1988, the year of Australia's bicentennial, the mainstream media shepherded the nation into celebrating the anniversary of British settlement, a massive insult to the ancestors of the aboriginal people who lived there for thousands of years before colonization. Aborigines and activists examine the media's role in molding together the geographically isolated urban pockets of modern Australia's population. This creates a technologically supported collective consciousness or "Technonationalism" in which the country depends on the media to string together a national identity. The bicentennial television special "Australia Live", with the voice of imperialism narrating. The video highlights how Aboriginal media provides an alternative to the mainstream by promoting aboriginal music and artists. It also gives the aboriginal community a political voice to fight against institutionalized racism.
      Speakers include Anna Munster, Noel Sanders and Jannette Nolan from Aboriginal Radio, Lorretta Fogarty and Chris Kirk Brigh an indigenous lawyer, linguist, and lecturer.
      This PTTV video, in collaboration with the Aboriginal radio station Radio Redfern and the Sydney-based video collective TAPS won a Hometown Video Award.
      1988 TRT: 55 minutes #154
    - Page Dubois Reads Plato, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0152)
      Page Du Bois Reads Plato
      Page Du Bois interprets classic Plato.
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #157
    - Greg Ulmer on Telerevisioning Literacy - Master, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0153)
      Greg Ulmer on Telerevisioning Literacy
      Greg Ulmer on literacy and learning.
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #160
    - The Image at the End of the Tunnel: Vietnam Nostaligia Grips the U.S. Media - Edit Master - Audio channel 2, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0154)
      The Images At the End of the Tunnel
      Bill Eisman speak of how Vietnam nostalgia grips the U.S. media.
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #162
    - Martin Lucas Watches "No" Video: The Chilean Plebiscite on TV - Edit Master, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0155)
      Martin Lucas Watches "NO" Video: The Chilean Presidential Plebiscite on TV
      Lucas covered the Chilean presidential plebiscite for European TV.
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #164
    - Fighting The Fig Leaf - Master, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0156)
      Fighting the Fundamentalist Fig Leaf
      The Mapplethorpe/Serrano controversies sparked a pressing debate on censorship of the arts. Artist David Avalos, Washington Project for the Arts' Philip Brookman, critic Coco Fusco, poet Allen Ginsberg and painter Leon Golub discuss the issues at stake. What is the conservative agenda behind arts censorship and what can we do to combat it?
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #165
    - Fighting the Fundmentalist Fig Leaf with Dave Avalos, Philip Brookman, Coco Fusco, Allen Ginsberg, Leon Gloub - Edit Master, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0157)
    - Fighting the Fundmentalist Fig Leaf - short verion - Edit Master, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0158)
    - Smurfs. Toys R U.S. Mark Dion, 1989 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0159)
      Toys "R" Us: Mark Dion Explicates The Smurfonomics of Smurfs
      Mark Dion explicates the smurfonomics of Smurfs.
      1989 TRT: 28 minutes #169
    - Torn Between Colors: Youth and the Media Through Our Eyes Video and History Project, Bronx Satellite High School, January 16, 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0160)
      Torn Between Colors: Youth and the Media
      Produced with the Through Our Eyes Video History Project, Black and Latino high school students of the Schomburg Satellite Academy in the South Bronx look at the media portrayal of defendants in the Yusef Hawkins Bensonhurst murder and Central Park rape cases. What role does the use of language and image have in constructing public opinion around racially charged cases, and more importantly, how do these representations mirror a racist system which continually denies minorities access to equal justice? This video shows a demonstration of how youth are using media production to take control of their own images.
      1990 TRT: 23 minutes #170
    - Zero Tolerance: J Tony Serra Cross-examines the "War on Drugs" - PTTV West, 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0161)
      Zero Tolerance: Tony Serra Cross-Examines Bush's War on Drugs
      Tony Serra cross-examines President George Bush Senior's "War on Drugs".
      1990 TRT: minute #171
    - Armond White Analyzes Do The Write Thing: Critical Advocacy - Master, 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0162)
      Do the Write Thing
      Film critic Armond White analyzes the film reviews of Spike Lee's "Do the Right Thing".
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #172
    - International Working Women's Day 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0163)
      Celebrate Sisterhood! Seize the Day! Women Take to the Streets of NYC
      This episode catalogues the major protests and speeches of the highly anticipated International Working Women's Day in NYC. It covers action all over the city, from marches for women's healthcare resources at NYU, to protests for reproductive rights in the South Bronx. Touching on women's struggles from South Africa to Nicaragua and crucial issues like women's labor rights and wages, HIV education, and military spending, the scope of this video spans far more than just the island of New York City; it crosses borders to unearth the larger and more insidious war against women that has been taking place all over the world.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #173
    - Drawing the Line at Pittston, 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0164)
      Drawing the Line at Pittston
      "Drawing the Line at Pittston" documents the 1989 coalminers' strike against the Pittston Mine Company in Virginia, West Virginia and eastern Kentucky. This strike proved to be a dramatic symbol for unions everywhere as supporters from around the world rallied behind the United Mine Workers. Although, this immense demonstration was one of the biggest US labor strikes in the last fifty years, it gained little to no coverage in the mainstream media. Through a series of interviews with strike workers, their families and local religious and community leaders, PTTV attempts to illuminate the gradual political awakening of a working-class community that was nearly swallowed up by the machinations of corporate greed.
      1990 TRT: 1 hour #174
    - Drawing the Line at Pittston - Master Edit, 1990 (Box 63, Media ID: 276.0165)
    - Batman - Edited Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0166)
      Herb Schiller vs. the Bat Lords of the Global Village
      Herb Schiller rereads Warner Brothers' Batman as an unsettling representation of the global media empires of the 1980's. Schiller's critique identifies the neurosis of a society, that places the hope for its salvation in the hands of the impossibly benevolent billionaire figure of Batman. Whether it is Bruce Wayne in the film or the corporate conglomerate Time Warner, behind the scenes, Schiller intones social change and civic justice are portrayed as ideas changed through the machinations of the superrich rather than by the actions and desires of the people.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #177
    - This is A Sex Advertisement: PTTV Reads the Catholic Bishops' PR Campaign, May 23, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0167)
      This Is A Sex Ad
      An exposé of the Catholic Church's anti-choice public relations campaign.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #180
    - Going for the Green: Bill Winberg Looks at the Corporate Markeing of Earth Day and Environmentalism, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0168)
      Going For the Green
      Journalist Bill Weinberg looks at the corporate marketing of Earth Day and the environment.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #181
    - U.S. Bans Abortion Title Ten Restrictions: A Policy That Kills, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0169)
      US Bans Abortion? Title X Restrictions: A Policy that Kills
      Questions about the effects of Title X, 'the gag rule', denying counseling on the legal right to an abortion. Produced in collaboration with WHAM.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #182
    - PTTV Special on Middle East with Coalition to Stop U.S. Intervention in Middle East, September 20, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0170)
      PTTV Responds to the Middle East Situation
      Paper Tiger Television visits a meeting of the Coalition to Stop US intervention in the Middle East. Lawyers, Vietnam Veterans, and community activists take the podium to voice their outrage over the approaching Gulf War or "War for Oil." Each speaker covers a wide range of important topics from US oil dependence and the development of alternative fuels, to war resistance and conscientious objection, to the growth in military spending and the erosion of social services and domestic funds. This tape looks into the earlier hypocrisies of US policy in Iraq.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #185
    - Kids Views on News: Carla Seal-Wanner and Children's Express Watch TV News - Edit Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0171)
      Kids Views on News
      With Carla Seal-Wanner and Children's Express of the children's news service.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #186
    - Kids Views on News: Carla Seal-Wanner and Children's Express Watch TV News - Dub Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0172)
    - The Silence That Silences, Robert Kinney, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0173)
      The Silence that Silences: Bob Kinney reads Rosilind Solomon
      Independent producer Bob Kinney analyzes Rosilind Solomon's photographs of people with AIDS.
      1990 TRT: 25 minutes #187
    - Robin Andersen Exposes the Real Deal: The CIA-Cocaine Connection - Saying NO to Drugs - Edit Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0174)
      Robin Andersen Exposes the Real-Deal: CIA-Contra-Cocaine
      Robin Andersen talks about the CIA- Contra-Cocaine Connection.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #188
    - Daily News: New York's Hometown Strike - Edit Master - split audio tracks, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0175)
      New York's Hometown Strike
      Labor, media, and the The Daily News strike.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #190
    - Panama - Edit Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0176)
      Operation Unjust Cause
      Robert Knight discusses the 1989 U.S. invasion of Panama.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #191
    - Ads! Ads! Ads! Mark Crispin Miller - Edit Master, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0177)
      Ads! Ads! Ads!: Mark Crispin Miller Journeys Through the Expanding Geography of American Advertising
      Mark Crispin Miller examines the advertising world before and after television. With the advent of TV, ads that were once in danger of being ironized by their socio-political surroundings become buffered from the contradictions of the outside world. What results, says Miller, is "an internal policing of the spectacle." He also discusses the effects of product placement within American films.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #192
    - T.V. Turn On, Public Access Show, 1990 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0178)
      TV Turn On: Stepping Up to the Electronic Soapbox
      PTTV takes a look into the public access world and answers its own crucial question, "why is public access TV so important?" During the renegotiation of the Manhattan cable TV contract, demonstrators and community supporters meet outside Time Warner to demand sufficient access to cable television equipment, facilities and administration in order to create a truly democratic media. Produced by Cathy Scott and Amy Melnick. Featuring Mary Ying Welsh, Mary Feaster, Simone Farkhondeh, Linda Iannacone, Joel Katz and Shu Lea Cheang.
      1990 TRT: 28 minutes #193
    - Operation Storm The Media - Master, 1991 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0179)
      Operation Storm the Media
      This show explores the relationship between corporate sponsorship and media censorship via coverage of the "Challenge the Media" demonstration in NYC in January 1991. PTTV and Renu Nahata from FAIR (Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting) comment on the media's packaging of the war. Winner of the 1991 Visions of the US video competition.
      1991 TRT: 28 minutes #195
    - The Middle East Crisis: Whose War is it Anyway? - Edit Master - Central Park East tape, 1991 (Box 64, Media ID: 276.0180)
      Whose War Is it Anyway?
      Produced with students at the Central Park East High School.
      1991 TRT: 28 minutes #198
    - Access-Able / World? What World? Dub-Master / Edit Master - unmixed audio - Master, 1987 / 1991 (Box 65, Media ID: 276.0181)
      Access-Able
      Paper Tiger workshop on public access at NFLCP.
      1991 TRT: 28 minutes #199 ----
      In a sampling of Paper Tiger works on world politics and the mainstream media, Herb Schiller, on the New York Times, and Brian Winston, on TV news, cover issues such as terrorism and the New World Information Order. This video presents an overview of media analysis and is used as a precursor to other more specific Paper Tiger programs.
    - Carlos Fernando Chamorro Reads Barricada - Master, 1991 (Box 65, Media ID: 276.0182)
      Carlos Fernando Chamorro Reads Barricada
      Carlos Fernando Chamorro gives a critical reading of Barricada.
      1991 TRT: 28 minutes #212
    - Joel Kovel Reads Bill Moyers - New Edit - Master (with Mutiny Tag), October 23, 1991 (Box 65, Media ID: 276.0183)
      The Devil & Mr. Moyers: Joel Kovel Tweaks the Halo of PBS